# Housam Babiker

+1 780 292 60 41 | khalifab@ualberta.ca | housamkhalifa.github.io | github.com/housamkhalifa

## Profile Summary

Recent PhD graduate in Computing Science from the University of Alberta. Published four top-tier conference papers (2 COLING, 1 ECML-PKDD, 1 EACL) out of my PhD project. Research interests include explainable AI, deep learning, reinforcement learning, and their applications to real-world problems.

#### **EDUCATION**

PhD in Computing Science University of Alberta	Sep. $2016$ – Mar. $2023$ Edmonton, Canada
MSc in Information Technology  Multimedia University	Nov. 2013 – Oct. 2015 Melaka, Malaysia
BSc in Information Technology  Multimedia University	${ m Jun.}  2007 - { m Jan.}  2011$ ${ m \it Melaka, Malaysia}$

### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- 6. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, Randy Goebel. Locally Distributed Activation Vectors for Guided Feature Attribution. In the 27 International Conference on Computational Linguistics (**COLING 2022**). Gyeongju, South Korea. (Acceptance rate: 33%).
- 5. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, Randy Goebel. Neural Networks with Feature Attribution and Contrastive Explanations. In the European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (**ECML-PKDD 2022**). Grenoble, France. (Acceptance rate: 26%).
- 4. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, and Randy Goebel. DISK-CSV: Distilling Interpretable Semantic Knowledge via Class Semantic Vector. In the 16th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (**EACL 2021**). Kyiv, Ukraine. (Acceptance rate: 24.7%).
- 3. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, and Randy Goebel. RANCC: Rationalizing Neural Networks via Concept Clustering. In the 28 International Conference on Computational Linguistics (**COLING 2020**). Barcelona, Spain. (Acceptance rate: 32.9%).
- 2. **Housam Babiker** and Randy Goebel. An Introduction to Deep Visual Explanation. In Neural Information Processing Systems (**NeurIPS-Workshop 2017**). Long Beach, USA.
- 1. Housam Babiker, Randy Goebel, and, Irene Cheng. Facial expression using SVM classifier on salient mic-macro patterns. In the International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP 2017). Beijing, China.

#### Relevant Experience

# Machine Learning Engineer

Nov. 2019 – Present Edmonton. Canada

 $AltaML\ Inc.$ 

- Developed NLP models for different domains (e.g., predictive models, semantic search, model in the loop, keyword extraction) and presented the findings to senior executive management.
- Developed a deep learning model to analyze legal cases by extracting facts, issues, analysis, and conclusions from legal documents. Project link
- Worked on models compression to improve the inference speed (e.g., quantization, TensorRT).

# Graduate Research Assistant

Sep. 2016 - Mar. 2023

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

- Developed XAI techniques for deep learning at the XAI lab under the supervision of Prof. Randy Goebel.
- Worked on building models to explain an RL agent for autonomous driving (techniques used: computer vision and natural language processing).

Teaching Assistant Fall 2018

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Prof. Joerg Sander and Sadaf Ahmed's teaching assistant (TA) for CMPUT 174: Intro. to the Found. of Computation I.

Teaching Assistant Fall 2017

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Prof. Anup Basu's TA for CMPUT 414: Introduction to Multimedia Technology.

Teaching Assistant

Fall 2016

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Prof. Janelle Harms' TA for CMPUT 101: Introduction to Computing.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

**Programming:** Python (7 years), Matlab (3 years), C# (1 year), C++(1 year).

Deep Learning Frameworks: TensorFlow (5 years), Keras (3 years), PyTorch (1 year), OpenCV (1 year).

# Selected Honors & Awards

- Mary Louise Imrie Graduate Student Travel Award, University of Alberta, Canada, 2022.
- Highest performance on task 4 of the COLIEE Competition, Japan, 2018.
- GSA Travel Award, University of Alberta, Canada, 2017.
- Champion of Infineon-MMU Technical Poster Session, Multimedia University, Malaysia, 2014.
- Champion of Infineon-MMU Technical Poster Session, Multimedia University, Malaysia, 2013.
- Best of the Best Award, International Conference and Exposition on Innovation of Institution of Higher Learning, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, 2013.
- Research Scholar Award, Multimedia University, Malaysia, 2013.